pwd                       # print working directory (where you are now)
ls                        # list files in the current folder
ls -l                     # long view: permissions, owner, size, dates
ls -la                    # include hidden files (those starting with .)
cd /                      # go to root directory
cd ~                      # go to your home directory
cd -                      # jump back to your previous directory
cd /path/to/folder        # go to a specific folder
clear                     # clear the terminal screen (just visual)
